Okay, so the recording started so we can
start. Okay. Um, welcome everyone.
Thanks for coming to the RL theory
seminar. I guess this is the first in a
series of talks we'll do for the I don't
know mid the spring quarter or whatever.
Um, the first talk for the for the
series is by Max Simcoitz. Um, it's my
great pleasure to introduce him. I've
known Max for like almost 10 years and
in that time he's had quite a you know
dynamic research career spanning topics
in learning theory, core reinforcement
learning theory, control, fairness, all
sorts of things. He's very strong, very
capable. Um he did his PhD at Berkeley.
He spent some time at MIT as a posttock
and now he just started as an assistant
professor at Carnegie Melon. and um he's
going to tell us about imitation
learning in continuous spaces and I
guess some pitfalls there. Um just for
admin stuff I think it's okay to do
questions during this during the talk if
you don't want to do that you can like
raise your hand I'll monitor or you can
just type in the chat and I'll interrupt
or you can also interrupt I guess uh as
appropriate. Um with that Max take it
away. Hi every thanks for thanks for the
introduction and thanks everyone who
took the time to make it to the to the
seminar. Uh yeah. So um maybe a little
bit about my journey before I begin is I
I did sort of a PhD in kind of more
traditional learning theory, but I had
the fortune to spend a few years in a
robot learning lab, a robot lab in MIT.
And I think it's really changed how I
think about some of the problems and how
it it's caused me to reflect on how some
of the assumptions that we make in RL
and RL theory uh might need to be
adjusted if we start thinking about the
continuous action world. And so I'm
going to present some work that kind of
tries to make some of these points a
little bit more clear.
So um maybe it's kind of every talk in
machine learning it feels like one is
obligated to begin with language models
and so you know one way to view language
models is uh just some form of expert
learning or learning from an expert
right so we can view natural human
language as an admittedly imperfect
expert and here what we're trying to do
is condition on observations in this
case sequences of previous tokens and
the action that we're trying to predict
is simply what is the next token in the
sentence that we want right a natural
model of what's going on in in
languages. Uh and we can think about a
similar paradigm occurring in large
robotics models as well. Right? So right
now people are are actively collecting
data to train large foundation models
for robots. And again with one way
they're doing this is they're collecting
large amounts of human demonstrations.
So there is this is from collaborators
at Toyota Research Institute. They're
collecting uh human demonstrations of
interaction with the robot and they're
and the aim is just to train the robot
to predict the next action the
demonstrator would give. again using
observations like pixels or tactile
sensing as a form of a conditioning
variable right so similar
paradigm so I think a couple questions
we can ask is you know looking at the
language model of regime will scaling
solve the problems of robotic foundation
models uh what is the importance of on
policy data uh we need for robot models
or can all this done purely from offline
demonstration and maybe how should we
design the forms of the robot policies
that we need in order to scale up these
systems right these are some questions
that we should keep at the back of our
heads
And so when I think about these
problems, I see a lot of formal
similarities, right? In language, my
goal is to predict tokens, whereas in
robotics, my goal is to predict actions,
but maybe in language, they're discreet,
and in robotics, they're continuous. And
I guess a major question is, are these
things meaningfully different or are
they just somewhat superficial in their
differences? Right? So is there a
fundamental difference here? So maybe we
can set up, right? So in in if you open
up an RL book or an RL text RL textbook
maybe RL theory paper what you'll see is
the following notation. You'll see
states denoted with the letter S actions
denoted with the letter A and you'll
denote dynamics as being drawn from some
transition probability distribution
transition kernel denoted as in the
slide and maybe a policy is just some
distribution of reactions again denoted
typically in this way. And in in
robotics or in control kind of we use
somewhat different notation, right? So
here we use x for states and actions are
u control inputs. Our dynamics rather
than thinking of them as coming from
some arbitrary conditional distribution.
We envision having some nominal dynamics
function typically denoted f and maybe
there's some noise that affects the
dynamic process. And then finally again
we can draw control inputs from some
policy some policy
distribution. So maybe the semantics
here are somewhat different right? So in
language models our states oftentimes we
think about this as being say sequences
of tokens maybe words right and our next
action is the next word whereas sort of
in robotics sort of uh we think more of
x as as being either observations or
system state used being a robot action
but notably these are continuous value
right so a lot of formal similarities
but maybe slightly different semat
semantics so in both problems we want to
say imitate an expert so what's a
reasonable way to talk about imitation
what we can do is we can look at some
notion of excess cost. So we can fix
some notion of cost. We'll call it C.
And our notion of error will be looking
at the cost under the imitator policy
which we call pi hat. This is what we
learn with data. And we compare this to
the cost under the expert, right? And so
our notion of excess cost, you could
call this regret. Basically determines
how well we're doing imitation, right?
And typically in this problem, we're
going to focus on problems over a
certain horizon, certain number of of
steps, which we'll denote by H. And
horizon will become kind of a key factor
in our discussion.
Right? So there are a lot of ways that
you can kind of try to minimize this
imitation error. So one possible way to
do this, not the only way is through
imitate is through what's called
behavior cloning. So in behavior
cloning, what you do is you specify some
loss function which and here I'm going
to be using the control notation X and U
which basically measures how well your
policy is doing relative to pairs of
states and actions in your expert uh
from from the expert data. Right? And
there are many loss functions that you
can minimize. And basically you just
train pi hat to fit the expert data by
minimizing this loss at least to the
best of your optimizer's
ability. So you might do this by
minimizing a square loss if you'd like.
Uh this typically works if pi star is
deterministic. You might do this by
minimizing an indicator loss. This
probably makes more sense if pi lo pi is
discreet. Uh you can use the log loss.
So Dylan's got some awesome work about
why that might be beneficial to work
with. Also works if pi has some
continuous density. uh or you could even
use things based on score matching which
have become quite popular in in sort of
diffusion polic parameterized policies
right that also works quite well and
it's very popular in robotics but sort
of kind of importantly is even if you're
not going to do uh sort of minim
explicit minimization of the lit loss I
think it is very natural to compare to
the the sort of best you could hope for
under minimizing this loss as a
benchmark of how difficult the problem
is at least statistically right so what
we'll do in today's talk is we'll
compare our notion of imitation error to
basically what we would expect to get if
we were just looking at how big the loss
was but in uh but in but crucially under
the distribution of expert data. So we
look at the distribution of expert data
this is this expectation and we measure
how large the losses and roughly
speaking we'll try to understand this as
a proxy for how easy the problem is
statistically without dealing with
issues related to the dynamics of the
system just how easy it is to fit the
expert data even if we consider
algorithms that don't necessarily do
this minimization algorithmically.
Okay. So why is behavior cloning hard?
Well, it it relates to this phenomena
called compounding error, right? So our
our notion of expert imitation accuracy,
right? How close we'd be on to fitting a
supervised learning objective on the
expert data. Uh you know, you can really
think about this as basically taking
samples from an expert trajectory and
making sure that you're able to make
predictions which at each individual
time step are close to what the expert
would do. Right? So this is what it
would look like to have a small notion
of our expert. But unfortunately what we
really care about is not our expert.
What we care about is sort of the
deployment behavior of the e of the
learn policy and what cost that attains.
So expectation under the learn policy pi
hat. And when you actually deploy the
learn policy what you start to see is
that the errors that it makes can
possibly add up. In fact errors can
accumulate over time steps and they can
in fact accumulate more and more largely
as the the horizon grows.
uh moreover after the error has
accumulated you can also run into the
fact that the fact that you might be out
of the distribution of your expert data.
So you might sort of end up somewhere
over here where you don't have a lot of
supervision and you don't quite know
what action to take next. Right? So this
is an issue that you can run into. So
what do we know? Well, it's very popular
actually even kind of going back to kind
of early work on imitation to compare
sort of imitation and uh uh imitation in
this sense to imitation this expert
sense. Let me cancel the software
update. Um and so for example, if we are
in a setting where we can minimize the
01 loss and we consider costs that are
bounded in 01, then roughly speaking, we
can bound our notion of imitation under
a certain cost that should have an R
subc by roughly h times uh the expert
error, right? Horizon factor times the
error of the imitation and the 01 loss.
And there's some really wonderful
improvements that can be made if you are
able to consider other loss functions
under certain kind of assumptions on
your function class.
Right? Uh and so what this basically
tells you is you know compounding error
is maybe linearish in the horizon
depending on how you parameterize
things. Maybe it's it's a little bit
better than that but it would seem like
compounding error the the horizon
dependence of your problem is not such a
significant
obstacle. So actually I'm going to say
that maybe this perspective is not the
one that we should take in the in the
continuous world and I'll justify why.
Right? So many forms of imitation
including ones that have been
popularized recently in LMS like log
loss really they sort of imply
guarantees that would imply imitation in
01 loss. So for example with Pinsker's
inequality you can sort of control total
variation distance by log loss. If that
doesn't make sense to you don't worry
about it. If you're an expert you
understand what I'm saying. So
essentially what what what basically
needs to happen is you need to be able
to imitate in 01 for any of these kind
of interesting sublinear or sublinear
guarantees to make sense. Okay. So
consider just a scalar prediction
problem, right? So I I just sample some
context vector uniformly from 01 and I
try to learn some function of that
scalar and suppose I just try to
minimize the 01 loss for just scalar
prediction, right? So here you know
these things might be continuous value.
This is possible. Uh for those of you
that know some basic statistical
learning theory, you'll say of course it
shouldn't be possible in general. In
fact, you can make this formal, right?
Right? So you can show that there are
classes of sort of just singlestep
functions where given n examples sort of
you can't get anything better in the 01
loss than not in the trivial error. So
the worst possible error in the 01 loss
is an expected error of one. But at the
same time you can actually learn let's
say in the L2 loss with vanishingly
small error. So you can make the error
go down as a function of number of
samples n as fast as you'd like and yet
you still can cannot learn in the 01
loss. Right? And this is kind of easy to
see. One way to construct this example
is to build a foraier series and show
that estimating in the 01 loss allows
you to uh perfectly recover every forier
coefficient. But sort of L2 estimation
just needs needs you to sort of
approximately recover the first few and
this is this is feasible from some
amount of data and you can actually make
the the rate of estimation improve as
you make the decay of the coefficients
go faster. Wait, Max, I'm a bit
confused. So here the class pi is not
known to the learner. Oh, it is known to
the learner. I sorry I I'll give you
I'll give you a class pi known to the
learner. So there exists a class pi
which is known to which I can tell you
tell the learner where I can't estimate
in the 01 loss but I can estimate in the
L2 loss and I can adjust that class for
whatever I'd like to make estimation at
L2 loss as fast as possible. I see. But
that class is not a singleton. That's a
large class. It's a large class. Yes.
Okay. Good. Good. Okay. Yeah. It's not a
singleton. Sorry. I should that's it
should be set of pi and pi. That's a
good clarification. Thank you. Thanks.
Cool. So basically the key implication
is that these assumptions under which we
get this linearish compounding error
they're not really applicable in in in
continuous state space right so all so
so far all I've done is convince you
that like thinking about 01 loss might
be the wrong thing for continuous state
spaces I haven't yet shown you that
compounding error necessarily might be a
problem so let me kind of make this a
little bit more
precise so to pro I I really like
proving lower bounds and one thing I
think is an important part of the art of
lower bounds is to prove them in
settings that you might otherwise think
are nice or benign
So the lower bound I'm going to prove to
you today is going to be in what we
might think of one of as one of the
nicest control systems that you could
think about. And let me try to convince
you that this is a nice system. So the
first thing that's going to be nice is
that the expert in the dynamics are
deterministic. In particular, there's
been a lot of work in robot learning
around learning multimodal policies,
policies that are complex distributions.
Instead, we're just going to think about
learning deterministic
experts. The second thing we're going to
assume is that the dynamics in the
expert are C infinity. They have
infinitely many derivatives and their
first and second of derivatives are
bounded, right? So they're going to be
lip shifts and smooth, right? Also a
nice property. So there's nothing like
stiffness or discontinuity of the
dynamics that's going to get in your
way. And the final property, which I'm
going to expend spend some time
explaining in a couple later slides, is
that the dynamics are exponentially
incrementally input to state stable.
This is a mouthful, but roughly what
this means is that the dynamics are
somewhat insensitive to perturbations.
So it's not the case that if you make a
small error suddenly you end up in a
totally different place. Roughly
speaking small errors shouldn't make a
big difference to the dynamics even on
longer horizons. And we'll talk a little
bit more about this
assumption. So we're going to get back
to that assumption later. I'm going to
explain it in greater detail. Last thing
what I'm going to say is that our lower
bound does not apply unconditionally. It
applies to basically any algorithm be
that online uh be that behavior coding
offline reinforcement in uh learning uh
inverse RL style approaches but it in in
particular constrains the class of
policies we're allowed to use. So we're
going to pro prove a lower bound against
what we call simple imitator policies
and then I'll explain to you at the end
of the talk how things generalize beyond
that. So I'm going to define a simple
imitator policy as a policy that has two
components. It has a deterministic
component which like the expert I'll
assume is lip shits and smooth and it
also has a stochcastic component which
is going to be assumed to be independent
of X. So we can see that simple policies
are a strict and and pretty strong
generalization of the kind of class of
policies that the expert can be but
nevertheless they don't capture every
policy. So for example, a common policy
parameterization in sort of like uh
simple robot learning tasks might be a
gausian a mean policy where you
parameterize the gausian mean but you
don't learn the gausian variance you
treat that as a fixed parameter or you
treat it as a fixed parameter across all
states and this would constitute being a
simple policy right not a non-state
varying uh uh variance in the
gausian and again for non-simple
policies actually that's where the story
gets very interesting that will be the
end of the talk so let me give you an
informal statement uh you can pick your
favorite number k favorite natural
number and what I'll show you is a
family of nice imitation learning
problems so a class of of pairs of
dynamics and policies which lies in
three dimensions only three dimensions
such that given n sample trajectories
there is an algorithm which can imitate
in let's say the L1 expert loss or you
can do L2 expert loss this also works
but you have to tweak things just a
little bit but can estimate you know uh
basically as fast as you'd like so it
can estimate at a rate of one over n to
the k right you can make k as big as you
But and so not notice that unlike the 01
loss, we actually now have a notion of
expert loss that can be imit can be
minimized and can be minimized provably
under a construction. Right? So what
this says is it says that supervised
learning on the distribution of the
action of the demonstrator is easy. It's
easy
statistically. But if you try to learn a
simple policy, there is a one lipits and
a bounded cost function. So a cost
function that's not too non smooth. It's
not unbounded such that if you try to if
you try to imitate and return only
simple policies, your error is at least
a constant times either like about one
either it's a constant error or it's two
to the horizon times your imitation
learning error. Right? So again you
can't that because costs are bounded of
course your your error can be at most a
cost a constant but in the regime where
the imitation learning is small it can
be at most a two to the horizon factor
larger. Right? Right. So this is a this
is a considerably larger effect of
compounding error than we saw in the
discrete setting which was linear in
horizon 2 to the
h. And again recall that this is
measuring the excess cost of the init
table relative to the expert. Right? So
this is kind of like the kind of big
result of our
findings. So a couple remarks right? So
I think the the most obvious one is now
the deployment error this r subcost is
exponentially larger than the expert
distribution error.
The second remark I think that's that's
kind of powerful is that um our result
depends on the structure of the imitator
policy itself and we'll see how this
arises from the proof but it doesn't
depend on the learning algorithm. So
behavior cloning, offline reinforcement
learning, uh inverse RL of the version
that doesn't use on policy data, just
tries to learn a reward and optimize it
offline. None of these approaches are
going to work, right? It's truly a
limitation of the policy class. And
finally, what we'll show is how to break
our lower bound with sufficiently
improper policies. And you know,
improperness has always been like a
really kind of powerful theme in in sort
of statistical learning. But we're
actually going to see that some of the
ways of being improper that break our
lower bound kind of give evidence to
some of the successes in recent robot
learning policies. And that'll be the
end of the talk showing how kind of
recent advances in robot learning
actually break our lower bound in kind
of interesting ways. So I think the
first thing that I'd like to do before
going into the kind of sketch of the
proof is to explain to you what I meant
by a nice control system in a little bit
more detail. So recall we assume that
our dynamics and expert are
deterministic and recall that we assume
that these deterministic functions are
both lip shits and smooth have second
you know bounded first and second
derivatives. But the real kind of weird
assumption that maybe the audience might
not be very familiar with is this notion
of stability of exponentially incre uh
incremental input to state stability.
And it's not really clear at this point
what this means. So let me kind of first
begin by pointing out what is
instability in control systems. Right?
Right? So a control system we can think
of a scalar control system. It's
actually linear where the dynamics as a
function of x and u are equal to twice
the state x plus the input u. Right?
This is a scalar control system. And so
let's consider two trajectories. Uh you
know one both trajectories start at the
initial state x equals z. In the first
trajectory your inputs are always
selected to be zero. But in the second
selected to be some number delta right
some small parameter delta. So what
happens when you plot these two
trajectories on the line? Well, your
first trajectory will always remain at
zero because you have a linear system
that starts at zero and you're always
putting zero in. But if you start
feeding in delta into the system, what
you can show is in fact basically the
magnitude of the state will grow by at
least twice to the horizon because you
get a factor of two here times delta.
Right? So we call this an unstable
system because the small perturbation
delta gets magnified exponentially by
the dynamics of the system. Right? This
is a kind of one of the simplest
examples of an unstable system, right?
So we can think of systems that have
high sensitivity to perturbations in the
inputs as unstable and that's kind of
their more kind of formal definitions of
this. So informally you can show that if
you have an unstable system uh basically
there there exist prop learning problems
which have which which are deterministic
which are smooth but are unstable and
every learning algorithm no matter what
you do will basically have exponential
compounding error uh for all
sufficiently large for for all horizons
that are smaller than exponential in the
dimension. Right? So what what this says
again is that our expert the policy is
easy to learn on the distribution but
when you try to deploy it you have
exponential compounding error and this
this this horizon less than a to the
dimension comes from the fact that you
can always cover the space. So there
it's kind of interesting there but
basically this says that there's nothing
that you can do in an unstable system
that will help you but in some sense
this is kind of like uninteresting right
so like again back to the art of proving
lower bounds it's not fun to prove a
lower bound in in a difficult situation
because we expect things to be difficult
if we if we expect our system to be very
sensitive to perturbations obviously
this is going to make compounding error
worse and moreover kind of from a
practical perspective instability shows
up a lot in classical control regimes
like aeronautics but we don't really
believe that robot learning is a stable
is an unstable problem We believe that
you know much of robot learning is sort
of very plastic. The robot has a lot of
compliance in its joints and so
instability while nice for proven
counter examples is maybe the wrong
paradigm to be thinking
about. So let's actually turn back to
nice systems systems that are stable.
And I'm going to introduce a definition
of if stability that we'll we'll explain
in kind of greater detail. So we say
this system is exponentially stable
exponentially input uh in incremental
input to state stable. It's a mouthful.
I'm just going to call it exponential
stability for now. If you take two
initial states and you take two sequence
of control inputs and they have the
following property that the difference
between the state at some time h + one
decays exponentially with some parameter
row between zero and one times the
initial norm between or distance between
the two states plus some basic kind of
like weighted geometric sum decaying as
row to the kind of distance of this of
that time step from the current time
step times the distance between the two
inputs. Right? Right? So this kind of
says that basically you have
exponentially fast attenuation of the
initial condition and distances in the
inputs towards the current differences
in the state. Right? You can think of
this as a forgetting condition. It
basically says that your system just
forgets things exponentially quickly
modulated by this parameter
row. So I'll give you an example of
this. Um if you uh if you had a system
of this form, you start at the same
states, but now you ch you perturb the
inputs by a factor of delta. What you
can show is that basically the
differences in the states will remain
order delta apart for all times t like
unlike the unstable system where things
are growing with t here all the states
are going to be close to one another. So
this is our notion of incremental
stability. So let me kind of explain how
this might look geographically or look
up sort of pictorially. So you can
imagine a system what we call open loop.
So this says I put in inputs to the
system and I see what comes out and
these inputs are not viewed as functions
of the state. So openloop incremental
stability says the following. It says if
I imagine some malicious adversary
that's going to take these inputs and
corrupt them by some amount delta. Then
the resulting out uh kind of response of
the system to these corruptions is going
to be roughly pretty close to the
original dynamics. Right? It just tells
you that these two things are going to
track each other pretty well as long as
this adversary is constrained to only
kind of making very small
perturbations. So that's incremental
stability. Perturbations of input lead
to bounded states. actually not very
small just sort of the perturbations
here are proportional to the
perturbations
here. Uh you can also talk about this in
closed loop. So in control and closed
loop what we mean is that basically the
dynam the inputs are being fed back into
the system. So we'll say that the expert
policy combined with the dynamics is
closed loop eis. If when we think about
feeding the expert back into the policy
right so into the dynamics so we take f
ofx your inputs are the the expert
policy evaluated at x plus some
perturbation. These also have the
stability property. So pictorially it
looks like this, right? So you take some
inputs to the control system. You get
out some states, but now your expert
policy depends on the states that are
that arise, right? So it clo it's what
we call in control closing the loop
feeding the states back into the policy.
And what kind of expert closed loop EISS
means is that the devil the kind of
adversary is allowed to slightly perturb
these inputs that the expert would have
taken put them back into the system see
the new state but crucially the expert
policy is evaluated on the new states
that the that the experts that that the
kind of adversary sees. So we call this
kind of incremental stability in the
sense that the adversary is only
perturbing over the expert but on its
own trajectory right and this is the
picture that we have here. So these are
kind of two very kind of nice desirable
behaviors that one might have in a
control system. And again this ensures
that these things are close. So
ultimately what we've done is we've
defined what we mean by a nice control
system. We're going to assume that both
the openloop dynamics right just the
dynamics itself but also the closed loop
dynamics what the expert would do are
both sort of exponentially insensitive
to perturbations. These perturbations
become forgotten exponentially quickly.
Right? And this is kind of the most that
you can hope for from both an expert and
from a dynamics function in terms of
being kind of regular and well
behaved. Cool. So again, right, what
does our theorem tell us? Our theorem
says even under this exponential
incremental stability uh uh condition,
we still have exponential compounding
error. And this should surprise you,
right? Because on the one hand I've told
you I have a property that makes my
systems exponentially forget errors
really quickly and on the other hand
I've told you that I have a I have a
setting where I can get do the learn how
to do the right thing but yet this
perturbations I make by like not
estimating perfectly compound
exponentially largely through the system
right so these two properties seem to be
at odds right the system forgets
perturbations exponentially quickly but
that learning is ex is sort of
exponentially sensitive to these
perturbations so I want to kind of
explain how it's possible for these two
things to be to co kind of coexist and
sort of to do this right to do this I'm
going to actually dive into a very
simple example from linear control
explain what can go on hey Max I have a
question
um so somehow in my head I'm I'm trying
to figure out why this is true also and
I'm um in my head I feel like actually
having noise in the dynamic could help
you because like once you make a mistake
you're like completely OD exactly
So having are like completely
uncontrolled in some sense but maybe if
there's noise you're actually not really
OD you're just like shifted in
distribution. Exactly. So noise in the
dynamics can help you a little bit
though your rates will your rates will
degrade with with noise. It actually
turns out in some follow-up work we're
able to show that you can use noise in a
way that doesn't cause the rates to
degrade with noise but nevertheless uses
noise to cover basically just what just
the bare minimum of what you need but it
doesn't follow through measure theoretic
arguments. Okay. So I think I think I
think that the thing that's kind of uh
that that that's that that so you're
right like you can go every you can for
example if there's noise in the system
you have uh you know absolutely
continuous densities you can even use
log loss but if you don't want to use
measure theoretic arguments and you kind
of want to understand things like purely
just sort of uh purely sort of
geometrically or control theoretically
um you yeah you're right that that the
absence of noise the the absence of
noise can make things more difficult um
but actually it turns out and we I won't
get to in this talk really what noise
buys you a better way interpret what
noise buys you as some sort of kind of
like geometric anti concentration rather
than sort of measure theor sort of
measure a probabilistic anti
concentration that's more of the correct
makes sense makes sense yeah yeah cool
cool question cool so let me kind of
explain but but here um so for example a
is asking this in part because Adam and
I and ash and others on the call maybe
were uh wrote a paper called butterfly
effects of SGD which you guys should
check out uh where we sort of show that
like policies kind of derail themselves
by going off distribution and they just
don't know what to do uh here we'll will
show actually that it's not that the
policy doesn't know what to do. It's
really that the policy cannot like
provably cannot figure out how to
respond. And I'll explain how this
works. So what we'll do here is we're
going to introduce linear control
systems very briefly. We'll explain what
incremental stability means for linear
control systems and we'll show how
there's actually a tension between
imitation and stability of these systems
and then we'll general gesture to how
one would prove a general result. So a
linear system is simply just a dynamical
system where the map is a linear
function and that linearity necessitates
that the map takes the following form xt
+ 1 is axt plus b
ut right so in particular if b is the
identity matrix then a linear system can
be shown to be exponentially stable if
and only if uh the spectral radius of a
which is denoted as the maximum
magnitude of the real part of the igen
values of a is strictly less than one.
So one maybe one way to see this is that
if you unroll the dynamics you get
powers of a and the spectral radius of a
basically dictates the behavior of the
powers. So if row a is less than one
these powers decay exponentially quickly
but if row is greater than one the
powers get exponentially larger. So
what's nice is we have a very kind of
easy way of characterizing stability for
make for for for linear systems of this
form. Cool. So um we can actually prove
like a nice little lema which says that
um if you have uh if you just you can
kind of compute that basically the
closed loop dynamics with linear
dynamics and a linear feedback policy.
So a linear feedback policy is just a
linear policy and it will take the form
uh pi of x= k * x and you can kind of
directly compute what the closed loop
dynamics are by feeding the linear
policy into the dynamics map right and
you can actually then show by computing
this and using the previous observation
that if b is the identity basically the
closed loop dynamics are exponentially
stable if and only if the spectral
radius of a plus the feedback map are
less than one and in particular um you
have exponential perturbation sity if if
the spectral radius of rope of of a plus
the feedback max map is greater than
one. Right? So this is kind of gives you
a nice characterization of closed loop
stability as well just using the
previous
slide. Cool. So in particular this means
if you have the following situation
where you have a matrix A and two
feedback kind of control matrices K star
and K hat. If row of a is less than one
but and row of a plus k star is less
than one but row of a plus k hat is
bigger than one you arise in the you you
find yourself in the following
situation. First row of a less than one
means that the openloop dynamics are
eis. The situation row a plus k star
less than one means that the closed loop
dynamics under an expert are also
exponentially stable. that expert is
just playing Kstar X. But now if your
imitator policy was trying to play K
hat, then in fact you would be
exponentially sensitive to perturbations
uh under the imitation dynamics. Right?
So if K hat is your imitator, then you'd
be exponentially sensitive to
perturbations, right? So what this
suggests is basically um uh so basically
uh let's see if this is important. Um,
so kind of what this looks like is is
that basically you have low error
sensitivity for both your open loop and
your expert. But somehow when you try to
learn the policy itself, you get
something that just can go off the rails
really
easily. So to prove a lower bound then
we want to basically show that we're in
a situation where something like this
can occur, right? We want to show that
we're in a situation where where where
our k stars can have this kind of
spectral property, but any k hat we
learn is strictly greater than one. And
I'm not going to show you the exact
matrices, but in fact we can show that
there's actually just 2x two matrices. A
pair of 2x2 matrices that have the
following properties. So the matrices
are such that the spectral radius of AI
and AI plus k star i. This is like think
of this as the expert controller for
this pair are both strictly less than
one. Right? So what this is telling us
is that basically that the that both
open and closed loop were exponentially
stable for kind of the linear control
problem and the linear expert. But on
the other hand, what we'll set this this
pair exists in such a way that for any
matrix which could be learned from
imitation learning data. I'll explain
what that means in a second. Uh there's
going to be one system where the
spectral radius of ai plus k hat is
strictly greater than one stated
otherwise there will be one system where
k hat has to destabilize those systems.
Right? So we we can we so both of these
spectral radi are I mean both of these
systems are stable but whatever you
learn from imitation learning will have
to destabilize one system.
Okay. So, okay. So, this is this is what
we're showing. So, notice that obviously
there is a way to stabilize both
systems. The controller K equals0
stabilizes both systems because both
systems are open loop stable. So, we
need to show that this applies only to
K's which can possibly learn from
imitation learning data and let me
explain what this looks like. Okay. So,
what we'll do is we'll construct our two
systems. be stable and we'll also
construct them and this is sort of
related to ash's noise point to ensure
that basically the span of the the the
second canonical basis vector the E2
vector is an invariant subspace of the
closed loop dynamics under both systems.
So what this means is that if you roll
out the expert policy all the data you
ever see is along the vertical axis. You
don't see anything on the other axis.
So in particular, it's going to require
basically these systems, these two
matrices agreeing on this axis so that
they're indistinguishable or rather
we'll enforce that these two systems
agree on this axis so that they're
indistinguishable from this data. What
this means is that from my expert data
alone I cannot tell which system I'm in
and I can't identify this index
I. But now what we're going to show is
that if we restrict our attention to
controllers which agree with the data on
the vertical axis which agree with K
star on E2 these controllers these ones
that agree with the imitation data
necessarily destabilize one system right
so there will be exist there will exist
one system at least where this learn K
controller will have to destabilize it
now there might be another system where
this stabilizes but at least one will be
destabilizing one way you can think of
this is you can think that Kstar one
will destabilize A2 and Kstar 2 will
destabilize A1. But in fact, in fact,
any controller that agrees with both of
them on this on the vertical will be
destabilizing on the horizontal. Okay?
And we can show that there's an example
that just it happens to work that this
is the
case. Um, and so you can kind of imagine
using this to prove a lower bound. But
unfortunately, linear systems are sort
of too all or nothing to prove a lower
bound. What I mean by this is that sort
of if all of your data was ever on the
on sort of the vertical axis with linear
dynamics and no noise, you could learn
things perfectly. So you're never going
to deviate. So really what you need is
some kind of sophisticated way of
embedding this into a nonlinear
construction. And I'm just going to kind
of really kind of handwavely explain how
this kind of works. So essentially what
we're going to do is we're going to kind
of use a bump function to embed a
nonlinear problem that forces the
learner to make some mistake that will
kind of cascade into the first
horizontal direction. And then from then
on the problem will look linear. And
basically we're going to have learn some
sort of nonlinear uh some sort of
controller that will be forced to
destabilize along here. What's nice
about this construction is that it
allows you to basically embed arbitrary
supervised learning problems into the
bump function which is how we're able to
get away with with a result that has a
lower bound for any rate desired rate of
estimation under the expert
distribution. So we can kind of embed
any nonparametric learning problem over
here and we get two to the h times the
statistical complexity of that problem
over here. So it shows that the result
is actually kind of a whole template of
lower bounds rather than a specific
statistical one. Um one thing um okay
this kind of gives you the details of
how we kind of finesse it. Uh one thing
I should
mention though is where the simple
policies come in right and what what
actually is kind of required is that a
simple policy is basically one which is
locally linearizable. Right? By being
smooth with state independent noise, we
can actually tailor expand these
policies and that allows us to relate
the behavior of this simple policy to a
policy which basically behaves like a
locally linear controller which allows
us to invoke this linear this lower
bound. Uh things are a little bit more a
little bit more subtle than that and you
actually have to use some some work from
the unstable manifold theorem. But
that's kind of the intuition that you
should have is that if you're only using
simple policies, you're you're kind of
in a regime where you can only locally
do as well as the best linear
controller. And this is going to kind of
get you stuck.
So kind of maybe what's the core insight
then? The core insight is actually that
we we've seen control a tension a
fundamental tension between being
faithful to the expert right having to
agree with the expert along this axis
and stabilization of the unseen
dynamical modes being able to stabilize
what we don't see. And somehow what this
shows is that unless we're able to use
sort of policies that cannot be tailor
expanded we're not able to resolve this
tension appropriately. And that's kind
of the core insight from the from the
from the finding. Um, this is the RL
theory seminar and I've talked a lot
about stability, but I feel like it's
time for me to talk a little bit about Q
functions and to connect how stability
that how I think of stability relating
to kind of dynamic programming and other
tools that you might have seen. So the Q
function in deterministic control uh
this is review for everybody but like at
least in this audience but let me just
kind of say it right. Right? So in a
deterministic control system, you can
just write the Q function as the cost to
go under the dynamics and policy. Again,
deterministic policy starting at your
given state and your given input. Again,
I'll be quick because this is RL theory.
So here's cost to go.
So we all know the performance
difference LMA at least I think the
audience here knows it which basically
allows you to use telescoping to uh to
represent the kind of difference between
costs under an expert policy and a learn
policy by looking at the differences
between Q functions where what you do is
you look at the expectation of the Q
function under the expert. You look at
the Q functions that are induced by the
learner and you look at how these Q
functions differ if you chose the action
that would be prescribed by your
imitator versus the action that would be
prescribed by the expert and you look at
basically the difference between these Q
functions and and under the expert
distribution and this is an alternative
way to evaluate the difference in
performance. So what's quite nice again
this is policy the expert learner policy
the expert. So what's quite nice about
the performance difference perspective
is it lets you talk about how easy
imitation learning is in terms of the
expert distribution by reasoning about
the regularity properties of the Q
function of the learner. So I'll give
you an example of this. If the Q
functions are lip shits then you can
upperbound these differences by the
distance between pi hat and pi star.
Right? Right? So if Q is lipids as a
function of U, you can upper bound
these. And in particular, what this
means is that the cost imitation cost is
upperbounded by Lipshit's constant times
the cumulative norm difference between
pi star and pi hat. Right? So what this
would suggest therefore is that if you
have lipids key functions, you don't
have compounding error. You don't need
compounding error. Uh you you don't
encounter this.
So and there's actually some wonderful
work by Gokul Swami and his
collaborators that kind of generalize
this in terms of in terms of sort of
integral probability metrics where they
kind of relate sort of notions of
unexpert imitation to properties of the
Q function
class. So in particular low compounding
error is guaranteed by insensitive Q
functions and large compounding error
requires highly sensitive Q functions.
So maybe one way to reinterpret our
result is to say the following. If even
if we're in situations where the
dynamics are both openly and closed loop
stable, it is both hard to imitate the
expert and to learn a Q function that is
lipchits and to learn a pi hat which
ensures that you get lipits q functions
with your with uh in closed loop with
the dynamics and I think this is kind of
an interesting message uh for us as RL
theorists where we're very naturally
inclined to make assumptions directly on
the Q function class. So statistical
complexity of the Q functions,
realizability, maybe smoothness
assumptions. But this actually says that
if you think about systems from a
dynamical point of view, you should
actually think about letting assumptions
in the Q functions emerge from the
dynamics rather than imposing those
assumptions a priority. And indeed, what
your Q function class should actually
look like might be something that's far
less regular than you might want. But
this might be absolutely unavoidable
even if the dynamics are nice and even
if your learn policy is in some
reasonable class. I think that's that's
I think this is something that really I
I I didn't really fully appreciate until
I until I until I started thinking about
the control setting. We also have some
upcoming work that we submitted to CDC
that will that that that um we're
excited to share where we actually show
some interesting equivalences between um
oh yes Naan has got a question which I
definitely want to answer. Naan yeah so
uh so for this case um if if you examine
the Q functions um in your lower bound
constructions are they nice and
luxurious for the they have to for the
expert policy for the expert policy for
the expert policy they are. Yes. So for
the expert policy they will be because
the expert policy is in exponentially
stable which will mean that the Q
function is going to be is going to be
lejits. Yeah. So then regarding messages
I wonder if uh there's an uh opposite
interpretation that is if you take the
approach of like learning Q functions
and you learn Q functions from a sort of
uh you know smooth ellipticious and nice
structure does that somehow maybe help
you enforce you to slap onto the expert
Q function? can't. No, it can't because
because the the point is that our lower
bound actually shows you can't even
learn a stabilizing policy and if you if
so if you could learn a policy which
ensured that you had a lip Q function
that would necessarily mean pihat is
stabilizing but the point is that you
cannot learn at least when you restrict
to simple policies you cannot learn a
stabilizing policy which means that it's
impossible to learn a policy that gives
you a lipids q function stated otherwise
our lower bound is agnostic to the
algorithm so there's really nothing you
can do on the algorithmic side. In fact,
yeah, I know that that lower bound is
Yeah. Yeah. I I guess I'm I'm like my
last question is like more general like
because that lower bound really says
that it you necessarily needs to change
your policy class, right? I think that
so the question I'm saying like more
generally like could you use could you
try to use the Q function to do this?
Yeah. Um I think it's it's certainly
it's certainly possible that you could I
think people have tried to do this.
There there's some I think some work
from Steven 2 from a few years ago that
tried to explicitly enforce stability
which is equivalent to enforcing
lipidness of the Q function. Um but it
actually turns out that the better thing
to do is just to make sure that you have
enough that you collect a little bit
more online data or you use a slightly
better expert to collect data. Yeah. and
working through the through the Q
function class. Presumably, if you were
in a setting where you had like really
good notions of like world models, you
for example, if you had really good
world models, you could try to enforce
stability of lipidness of the Q function
as an algorithmic tool. You could also
try to just enforce stability of the
dynamics. These two are kind of
essentially in our in our follow-up
paper, we're showing that these are dual
to one another. So any algorithmic thing
that tries to pre-p prune Q functions is
basically the same thing as any
algorithmic thing that tries to afford
dynamic stability.
um it's basically like an IPM
characterization of stability rather
than than of optimality in terms of Q
functions. Um so but yeah I think it
would be an exciting it would be
exciting to see how to do that but from
what my understanding at least empirical
attempts to to to do stability
constraints uh have been quite difficult
and that suggests that maybe lipits
constraints in the Q class might also be
difficult on their own but maybe in
conjunction with other things they might
be powerful. Cool. Max I have a
question. Yeah. Um in this setting the
cost function is known or not known
known. Oh so yeah so in in the whole in
the whole in our whole construction the
cost function is known which means that
we we preclude offline RL which can even
use the cost function. You can't even
use the con function to to to beat our
lower bound.
Good. And you get trajectory data from
the expert or do you get like data?
Trajectory data.
Yeah. Trajectory data. Yeah. Uh okay
then maybe I'm surprised because somehow
you could say let me take a lip shits
function class and try to regress onto
classes. Yeah. So let me let me maybe
say this in a different in a in a
different way. So um you what you're
getting at is something called action I
think you're getting towards something
called action chunking which I'll talk
about in a second. But I should say that
one important thing is that basically
you're not your your set of instances
does not come from the product class of
of we're getting a little bit into the
weeds but does not come into the come
from the product class of of dynamics
and pies right so the point is that like
one pi star might not stabilize another
f and so we're in a regime where there's
not really kind of a clear way to just
sort of like um ensure that there's some
ground truth set where we could get lip
shitness or stability from. So I can I
can show you something else that will
work and that'll be kind of like the
last part of the talk. Okay. Um but I I
agree that it's kind of hard to regress
onto the problem is that you don't know
the dynamics in the construction and so
it's hard to reason about what will end
up being kind of lip shits because that
requires knowledge of the dynamics and
and that's where like online will be
really useful because then online.
Exactly. Yeah. Exactly. or some other
form of additional exploration which is
being discussed in in future work. But a
sort of crucially the lower bound
leverages non lack of knowledge of
dynamics. If you did know the dynamics
then there'd be a computationally
inefficient algorithm which either a
throws out all unstable policies or b
throws out all non- lipjits q function
policies with non-litsq functions. But
sort of crucially we don't know the
dynamics. If we did we would be able to
do much better. Yeah I I think okay like
I I think I'm also saying something
slightly wrong. Like if you do like
regression to learn a Q function and
then derive a policy by like acting
greedily according to
that that policy's Q function is not the
thing you learned. Exactly. That
policy's Q function might not be lipits
even though the Q function from which
you're deriving the policy is lift.
Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. In
Yeah. Exactly. And so actually and and
some followup work actually explaining
exposing like kind of the the the kind
of equivalence between lift and
incremental stability. I want to end the
talk on this note which is like how
weird continuous action spaces truly are
and the power of non-simple policies in
continuous action
spaces and this will kind of explain
some things that do work. So one is that
we need new notions of coverage. So why
is this? Well, we're doing imitation
learning which from a measure theoretic
standpoint from probability standpoint
we have perfect coverage. Our our rate
on negative derivative with respect to
the expert is one. Now we don't have all
policy coverage. We have perfect expert
coverage. But what we're able to show
even in this paper is that if there's a
certain notion of anti-conentration
which is less sort of measure theoretic
and more geometric uh in basically in
some which basically controls sort of a
local variance of of of expert data.
Think of this as induced by of
randomness over the initial state
condition. We can imitate without
compounding error. I'm going to for the
interest of time I'm going to be super
informal about this but basically what
this says is that like thinking about
coverage and continuous action spaces in
a more geometric or anti-conentration
way is more is is quite useful. The
intuition that you should have is
essentially you can learn a little bit
of a tube around the expert policy. I
should include a graphic about this and
this allows you to learn local tailor
expansions and by learning the local
tailaylor expansion you actually get the
controller right in a region which
allows you to stabilize. So we have some
results of this form and we were
actually strengthening them in some
future work but it really says that for
continuous action spaces it's important
to think geometrically not just
probabilistically and also there's some
work between with Adam Block and I on
some work in smooth online learning that
also has a more geometric take that kind
of has a similar takeaway
um uh maybe an algorithmic takeaway is
also thinking thinking about the work
the role of yes non one second is is
thinking about the role of data
collection as well yes none yeah so when
you say metric versus probabilistic
notion of coverage I guess probabilistic
you're talking about you know things
like density ratios of correct and for
metric do I interpret it as something
like you know near linear NDP you can
refine the coverage into something like
the sample coarance matrix and that sort
of thing and then linear dynamical
systems like you obviously also have
like you know the linearity and I I
think I think it's actually quite the o
o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o
o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o o
opposite so so in in linear systems or
like linear MDPs what you're what you
get you don't need coariant coverage you
coariance coverage. So you actually need
a you can get away with weaker notions
of coverage that depend on like moments
of the distribution. Yeah, that's what I
meant. What what we're saying is
actually need something stronger. So the
the coverage needed in linear settings
is actually weaker than sort of like
density ratio coverage because it's just
of a sufficient statistic. What we're
saying is we need something that's
actually ratio coverage. Yeah. Stronger
than density ratio coverage. Something
that actually kind of covers the nearby
metric space even though this is off
distribution of your expert. Right.
Right. Right. Right. That's a great
question. Thank you. Uh the second
thing, here's a cool little graph is
actually basically that more um uh uh we
can actually show that improper policies
are more powerful. So one thing that you
can actually do is you can predict
sequences of openloop sequences of
actions. We call them action chunks. And
it turns out that action chunks can kind
of like uh can kind of get around some
of these problems. Uh this is being made
more clear in future work. But basically
what they can do is if your s if your
expert is uh sort of closed loop stable
then it means that sort of the
perturbation of the input to the expert
uh to future actions is also going to be
kind of exponentially like stable. And
that means that if you learn a whole
sequence of chunks of actions you can
kind of predict multiple steps ahead and
have stability into multiple steps in
the future. And it turns out you can
actually feed this back into the system
in a way that preserves stability.
Unfortunately I don't have time to go
into this but needless to say there are
ways around this that are purely
algorithmic. And in fact we can actually
solve imitation learning in all uh
continuous action problems that are
exponentially input stable and open and
closed loop by action chunking. Here the
graph shows an experiment validating
this. So we use a diffusion policy to
imitate because that's very popular
today. The op the red openloop
trajectory. This is if we just like let
the system go with errors is is read is
is is is denoted in red. And basically
this is getting very little compounding
error. It's basically staying very close
to the system. Now we train a bunch of
different uh sort of diffusion policies
with different lengths of the action
chunks. We see that no using no chunking
leads to a huge very quick divergence in
the policy and as we use bigger and
bigger chunks we have more and more
stability. So this is kind of a really
interesting very strange effect that
that I think is is somewhat unique to
continuous action spaces. I want to save
questions to the end because there's
even more weird stuff that can happen.
Um in fact we can actually think about
instability in a very stylized way and
this will kind of be the last little bit
of the talk that I want to explain. So
imagine a scalar dynamical system where
you have some unknown sign of the
system. It's either plus or minus one.
You have a scalar parameter that's
strictly bigger than one that dictates
instability and you have some input you
can put into the system. So this is a
scalar system. It's unstable because row
is greater than one and you have an
unknown sign. So basically it says you
don't know which way the dynamics are
going to push you. You don't know which
way to cancel them
out. So one obvious kind of fact is that
if you don't know what C is, you don't
know the sign, there's no linear
feedback policy which will stabilize for
both choices of C. Right? And this is
sort of because like either your sign is
pointing you in one direction or it's
pointing you in another direction. And
so whatever your linear policy is, there
will be a sign that makes this magnitude
greater than one. Not so interesting. as
correlated to this by tailor expanding
there exists no smooth deterministic
policy which also locally stabilizes
your dynamics right because a smooth
deterministic policy can be locally
stabilized uh you can just argue this
with a with a tailor expansion argue
about linear approximation uh you can
even generalize this to show that
there's no simple policy one that's
basically a smooth policy plus state
independent noise which locally
stabilizes and again uh this kind of
follows from a similar tailor expansion
argument with a few more bells and
whistles um but what's kind of weird
is that there are some like really weird
policies that can stabilize this even
without knowledge of so let me give an
example uh this policy which is just
time varying stabilizes the system so
what happens right like the first time
you try to stabilize in one direction if
you're right good you're at zero and
you'll stay there if you're wrong you'll
just try the other way and that will
work this is kind of weird uh there's
also this other thing we call concentric
stabilization this is kind of related to
more classical kind of pathological
controllers in the control theory
literature
where basically you can just bin
diatically your kind of intervals on
both sides and you can have a switching
policy which decides which sign to use
depending on which bin you're in. So if
you kind of get the bin right you've
stabilized to zero. If you get the bin
wrong essentially if you choose things
correctly you end up in the next bin
over and that stabilizes you back to
zero. So notice this is like a highly
non smooth policy right because it's
going to get vanishingly less and less
smooth as you go to the origin. you can
smooth things out a little bit. So it
has a bounded second derivative, but
it's still going to have a singularity
here. So this is also like very very
strange. And the last thing you do you
can have is something called uh we call
benevolent gamblers rune which I think
is the thing that's sort of the most
shocking to me. So you can just learn a
policy which is uh with probability 1/2
either plays row of x or a negative row
of x. So it just flips its sign. And so
what this looks like is basically if you
look at the probabilities that you
haven't sent this to zero at each time
step with probability 1/2 you send the
dynamics to zero and you stay there
right so each time the chance of being
at zero is growing in probability and
the chance that you're not at zero is
getting bigger and bigger. So in
expectation you're actually like
destabilizing the system but we get this
benevolent gamblers's rune which is that
on like a very large probability event
you've stabilized the system and in fact
this is sort of related to a
technicality in the lower bound that
this this that the audience will
appreciate which is that we decided to
prove our lower bound not on L2 distance
from the expert but on costs that are
bounded. So our lower bound proves
against bounded cost to prevent us from
cheating using benevolent gamblers's
rune. We can't use that in our advantage
in the lower bound. But in fact this
actually shows that that this is sort of
that that actually moving to kind of
complex stoastic policies uh can
actually give you wins if you have
bounded costs which is kind of crazy. Uh
and I think this is actually quite
powerful. By the way we actually show
that all these these these kind of forms
of cheating the lower bound they
actually have coralates where we can
beat our construction by by using each
one of them. You can beat it by being
non smooth. You can beat it by using
benevolent gamblers rune. And I think
the benevolent gamblers's room to me is
kind of the most philosophically
interesting because if we go back to
kind of the purpose of improper
algorithms, it really comes back to a
game theoretic understanding of of of
sort of what learning is, right? We view
learning as a game between a learner and
nature that picks uncertain state of the
world. And we need to through
observations of that state understand
what to do. And we understand that
randomization provides some power of
dealing uncert with uncertainty in
games. And essentially what this
benevolent gamblers rune is showing is
that these kind of potentially these
very powerful ways of randomizing, very
sophisticated ways of randomizing are
actually necessary for playing this
imitation learning game correctly
against nature. Right? So these kind of
policies like the fusion policy which
are known to capture multiple modes in
the data, traditionally they've been
seen as being able to represent rich
action distributions. But it's actually
quite conceivable that they're doing
something even smarter. that even when
you're trying to imitate a deterministic
expert, there's some benefit to
randomization in a complex and state
dependent way that actually benefits
your that benefits your performance
because of the uncertainty over the true
state of the nature of the dynamics. And
I think this is something that's like
kind of crazy and was kind of shocking
to me after reflecting on on the
consequence of this. So maybe I want to
end on this. There's a surprising
takeaway here which is that stochastic
multimodal policies, things like a
diffusion policy, they can yield
benefits even for imitating
deterministic policies. Right? there is
like a there is a benefit of
improperness that resembles at least
some of the capabilities of today's
robot learning models. And I think this
is kind of kind of a a departure point
for what kind of a big theme in my
research today, which is understanding
what's going on with generative models
and control. So for those of you that
don't know, generative models have
become kind of the go-to architecture
for kind of continuous action control
the last two or three years. And I think
we really are only scratching the
surface of their full capabilities and
scratching the surface of understanding
why it is that they provide benefits.
And this this talk kind of shows that
even in very simple classical smooth and
deterministic settings, things like
generative modeling, things like action
chunking, some of these more complex
design decisions actually have, you
know, potentially very powerful
benefits. And I think there's a lot more
to learn to understand and to harness.
And I think with that, uh, I'm I'm happy
to take questions, maybe a little bit of
takeway for the RL theorists. Uh,
rethink key functions, rethink coverage,
uh, rethink pro policy
parameterizations. Uh, and thank you.
Awesome. Thank you, Max. Um, any quick
questions before we uh stop the
recording?
Uh, you mentioned action chunking. What
is that? Oh, so action chunking is the
practice of predicting multiple chunks
of multiple steps of the action um in
one go. So what you do is you ra so your
expert policy let's say predicts you
know U1 from X1 but you could also take
U1 U2 U3 and U4 and predict that whole
sequence from X1 and in some sense this
increases the representational demands
in the policy class but reduced horizon
well so one the naive benefit is it
reduces horizon but it actually turns
out that there's a critical threshold of
chunk length below which once you can
imitate that chunk length you actually
no longer pay compounding error.
And this is um something that's it's it
it basically has to do with the fact
that uh there will be a point at which
the openloop dynamics are sufficient.
Basically what action chunking is doing
is it's converting closed loop into open
loop and there will be a point at which
the openloop dynamics are sufficiently
stable that uh you you kind of uh drown
out the effects of like uh perturbations
in the policy. And if you can predict
chunks of precisely this critical length
or longer, you can kind of like drown
out some of the errors of your own of
your own learn policy. Um,
okay. So maybe is this maybe okay I'm
trying to understand it and here here's
maybe a too simplified way of thinking
about it. But um suppose in your problem
you have deterministic starting state
and uh you have deterministic systems
then effectively I could just memorize
the action sequence of the expert and
reproduce that. So I this is so it's a
little different than this. So if I just
memorize the distribution of the the
expert essentially the effect of this is
we're reducing the horizon right it's
just basically taking you from two to
the h two to the h over chunk length.
But it actually turns out that there's
another effect that's a little bit more
control theoretic which is that there's
actually a critical window of action
chunking such that basically there's the
the there's a a policy class which
includes the expert sort of realizable
policy class um where everything in that
policy class is now stabilizing. Yeah.
So so in that case like how does that
critical window how is that determined
like by determined by the parameter?
It's determined by the row parameter of
the of the system and determined by some
other lipids constants. So roughly speak
speaking it's going to look like log
base row of some lipids constants.
Um and actually so Nick Montney who was
on the call and one of his students
Thomas Jang and Dan Farmer and I are
kind of working on this as a follow-up.
That's one of the things we're also
working on kind of a more thorough
understanding of exactly how noising
affects things. So what we can show for
example and this might be of interest is
that if you add noise and you use kind
of more probabilistic or information
theoretic arguments you pay a trade-off
for your noise level. But if you use
kind of more control theoretic and
geometric arguments there ends up being
basically this like sweet spot the sweet
band of noise where you can add the
noise in. And no matter as long as you
add noise sort of in that sweet spot
region uh you get like the optimal you
get sort of like the correct rates and
it doesn't it's not really too sensitive
to the noise and there's no real
trade-off. And essentially one way you
can think about this is like you need to
learning how to stabilize is basically a
qualitative effect that you need to wrap
around the quantitative accuracy of your
policy. So really you just need enough
data that can teach you okay here's how
you kind of make sure I'm learning a
decent enough approximation to the
linear controller to stabilize off off
trajectory. And once you've learned that
you're golden and so we can show we have
some arguments that are based on tassel
which is kind of work from Dan Farmer
that show that you can do this with more
with more noise. So again, it's a very
different flavor of argument than than
what we typically see in some of the
kind of more measure theoretic
takes. But yeah, cool. Uh open to other
questions. Um maybe we should stop the
recording. Yes, I
can do that.